Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY
  - De emblemate. On emblems. Rhetorical figures (emblemata, schemata, etc.). 11-1/2 pages, numbered 125-130v. (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Hebrea Mater Galesi... Epistola. An epistle in Latin distichs in which a Hebrew mother relates the death of her child during the Slaughter of the Innocents. 3 pages, numbered ff. 131-132. (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Two Latin Poems. The first concerns San Luigi (Gonzaga); the second, Saint Ignatius of Loyola. 20 pages, numbered ff. 132v-143. (Box 11, Folder 29-30)
- NOTEBOOK
  A manuscript notebook in Latin, comprising 984 pages, numbered ff. 1-603. Possibly the note book of Giulio Riccio, pupil of Angelo Gallucci (1593-1674), professor of Rhetoric at the Jesuit College in Rome. Entry dates given are 1631 and 1637. Thick 8vo. Contemporary vellum. Rome, c. 1630-1640.
  - Eloquencia Salutaris. -Divinitatis laudavio. etc. Panegyrics on miscellaneous topics, from moral qualities to animals. Ms. in Latin. These panegyrics are made up of notes taken down by a student named Giulio Riccio (verso leaf 96), in the class room of his teacher Angelo Gallucio (professor of Rhetorics). The date is given as 1637. 188 pages, numbered ff. 4-96. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Theologia Flores cum Aliis quamplurimis Titulis. Theological topics like God, Christ, the Virgin, etc., in alphabetical order. Under each title, a set of descriptive phrases concerning the respective topic. 248 pages (many filled only partly), numbered ff. 119-242. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Rose descripcio. Description of the Rose. 4-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 243-245. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Sanctissimus ille Doctrina Mystagogus... A mystical treatise, author not specified, which seems to be inspired by a medieval mystic, probably St. Bonaventure. 108 pages, numbered ff. 266-319. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - De Passione Domini. -Oratio. by Francesco Piccolomini. 5-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 320-322v. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - De Passione Domini. -Oratio. by Stefano Zucchi, a Jesuit. 3 pages, numbered ff. 324-325. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - De Passione Domini. -Oratio. by Baldassarre Cittadella. 6 pages, numbered ff. 326-328v. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - De Passione Domine. -Oratio. by Leone Santi. 5 pages, numbered ff. 330-332. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - E'multis elegantibus lineamentis... A treatise based on the analogy between various type of angels and the representatives of the ecclesiastical hierarchy. 34 pages, numbered ff. 334-350v. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Rettorica Biblioteca. Lecture notes from a class in rhetoric. 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 353-356 and 25-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 361-373. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Tractatus de Epistolis. A small treatise on letter-writing. 11-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 375-380v. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Annotationes ex Oratione D. Tarquinii de innocentiae cede. On the Slaughter of the Innocents. 5 pages, numbered ff. 381-383v. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Orationis XXIV De Beato Aloizio Gonzaga. Selecte annotationes. Annotation on a panegyric eulogizing a Jesuit saint. 4-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 384-386. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Gemmarum Alphabetum. A collection of phrases describing gems, in alphabetical order, starting with Agathe. Also, flowers, giants, heros, etc. 11 pages, numbered ff. 389-394. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Formularium Liber. A collection of oratorical description: of a battle, actions in war, the panegyric of an unconquered general, and a description of a football match, etc. 4-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 395-410. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Oratiuncula... A short speech on the different activities of man. 3 pages, numbered ff. 411-412. (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Blessi Aloisii Gonzaga. An oration in praise of St. Luigi Gonzaga, presumably delivered by Giulio Riccio, in 1631, in a class of the Collegio Romano. 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 413-416. (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Virgo sine labe concepta... A speech in praise of the Immaculate Virgin Mary. 6 pages, numbered ff. 421-423v. (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Franciscus Xaverius...Oratio. A panegyric on St. Francis Xavier. 4 pages, numbered ff. 425-426v. (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - De Lacrimis. Treatises and various poems on the mystical significance of tears. 163 pages, numbered ff. 429-520. Contains also a panegyric treatise by Franciscus Brivius (see no. 22). (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Varia Genera Carminum. Various kinds of poems. 194 pages, numbered ff. 521-581v (some blank). (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Brivius, Franciscus. De Diva Catharina Panegiricus. Brivius (1597-1666) became a member of the Jesuit Order in 1614 and later professor of rhetoric at the Collegio Romano. A panegyric on Diva Catharina. 7-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 582-586v. (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Varia Carmina. 14 poems. 27-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 588-603v. (Box 12, Folder 23)
- SPINOLA, LAZARO. LIBRO...DE DIVERSE MATERIE
  - Spinola, Lazaro, Libro nel quale si trata de diverse materie utilissime ad agn'uno. Manuscript. Title page (some words affected by ink erosion) and 163 pages, numbered ff. 1-82. 8vo. Contemporary limp vellum. Milan, (1643). (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - A manuscript of contemplations on history, the pages fully covered in an easily legible 17th century hand, probably that of the author, who calls himself "abbate e priore."
- ORDEN, COMO SE HA DE GOVERNAR UN BUEN SOLDADO
  - Orden, Como se ha de Governar un Buen Soldado. Manuscript in Spanish. 77-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 1-39. Contemporary vellum. (Naples, 17th century?). (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - A calligraphically written copy of a manual on military regulations and organization, the duties of various officers, military groups, etc. The manuscript seems to be incomplete. The anonymous author was probably a Spanish officer of the 17th century in the service of the Viceroy of Naples.
- MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS, 8 printed pamphlets and 3 manuscript documents
  comprising 140 pages, numbered ff. 1-79, including 1 leaf manuscript index. 4to, unless otherwise stated. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, first quarter of the 17th century.
  - (Henry IV, King of France). Dichiarazione, et Ordine del Re Contente le Cagioni dell'haver mosso Guerra al Duca di Savoia. Manifest by the King of France, justifying his taking up arms against Charles Emmanuel I, Duke of Savoy. Translated from the French. Printed Pamphlet. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 2-5. Florence, Marescotti, 1600. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Apparently very rare, not in the catalogues of the British Museum or the Bibliothèque Nationale.
  - Discorso della Guerra fra i Genovesi e il Duca di Savoia nell'anno 1629. Charles Emmanuel I of Savoy was defeated by the Genoese. Manuscript. 20 pages, numbered ff. 6-16v. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Descrittion Breve di Ferrara nel cui dominio sia stata et sia. An account of Ferrara's history (then belonging to the States of the Church), and the different dominations under which it has been since the time of Charlemagne. Manuscript. 22 pages, numbered ff. 20-31v. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - La Restitutione di Clerac, con le parole tenute da quelli di Clerac, che hanno mandato verso il Re per rimetterli la piazza nelle sue mani ali 4 di Agosto 1621. Translated from the French. Printed pamphlet on the restitution of the Catholic religion in 1621, when Louis XIII seized the Huguenot strongholds. With a list of the cities that surrendered to the King. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 34-37. Venice, Antonio Pinelli, 1621. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Viaggio del Illmo. et Rev. Sig. Monsignor Ottavio Santa Croce Vescovo di Cervia, destinato da sua Santità per suo Nuntio alli XXIX di Marzo presso la Cesarea Maesta Rodolfo Imperatore all'hora residente per una Dieta in Praga nella Bohemia. An account of the trip of Ottavio Santa Croce, bishop of Servia and papal nuncio, to the Imperial Diet, held at Prague. Manuscript. 24 pages (the end is missing), numbered ff. 38-49v. N.pl., 1581. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Oratione, over Parlamento del Duca di Hernia, nel Conseglio di Spagna. Printed pamphlet. A speech dealing with the question of whether Spain should lay down weapons and forgive the Duke of Savoy (Charles Emmanuel I), or prosecute the war and despoil him of his territorial possessions and destroy the menace he represents to the State of Milan. 4 leaves (last blank), numbered ff. 50-52v. N.pl., n.d. (c. 1615). (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Breve informatione delle differenze, che passano con Monsig. Paravicino Vescovo d'Alessandria, per servitio della sua Chiesa, nella diffesa dell' Immunita Ecclesiastica particolamente. A printed pamphlet on the diffeences concerning ecclesiastical policy between Erasmus Paravicino, Bishop of Alexandria, and Rome, including letters to and by Paravicino, dated 1623-1626. 8 leaves, numbered in pencil 54-60. N. pl., n.d. (Rome, 1626). (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Relatione Della Rotta data dal Sig. di Toiras, Luogotenente di Monsù di Pernone per il Rè Christianissimo à Monsù di Subisse, capo d'Heretici Ribelli, di nuovo sollevato contro sua M. nel Paese di Modoc, nella Riviera di Bordeo. Printed pamphlet, translated from the French. An account of the defeat inflicted by M. Toiras, lieutenant of M. d'Epernon, upon M. de Soubise, leader of the rebellious "heretics." Soubise is Benjamin de Rohan, seigneur de Soubise, a leader of the Huguenots during the reign of Louis XIII. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 62-65v. Small 8vo. Paris and Rome, 1625. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Seconda Rotta dei Rebelli Heretici di Mont'Albano, data dall'Esercito del Rè Christianissimo. Printed pamphlet. Account of the second defeat inflicted upon the Huguenots by M. d'Epernon. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 66-69v. Small 8vo. Lyons, Rome. 1625. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Relatione del Negotiato Dalli Deputati di Savoia in Milano per l'accommodamento delle differenze con Mantova. Printed pamphlet. An account of the negotiations (1622) between the Dukes of Savoy and of Mantua concerning the settlement of a monetary dispute. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 70-73v. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Risposta alla Relatione stampata in Torino, Sopra el negotiato dalli Deputati di Savoia in Milano, per l'accommodamento delle differenze con Mantova. Printed pamphlet. A reply to the preceding. 12 pages, numbered ff. 74-79v. Leaf 79v contains a Relatione fatta al Signor Duca di Feria dal Sig. Conte Luigi Arconati, dated Milan, April 28, 1622. N. pl., n.d. (1622). (Box 15, Folder 11)
- GIOTTINI, P. L'ASTROLOGO
  - Giottini, P., L'Astrologo. Commedia. 89 ff. Ms. on paper. Small 8vo. Contemporary stiff grey wrappers. N.pl., n.d. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - This volume contains a comedy-play by a certain P. Giottini, L'Astrologo, which was apparently never printed. The roles of Tognello and Pulcinella are written in the Neapolitan dialect. Comic contrasts are obtained by exploiting the peculiarities of French, Florentine, German, and Neapolitan.
- COMMEDIA IN PROSA
  - A comedy play in 5 acts of the 17th century. No title is given. 99 ff. Ms. on paper. Small 4to. Contemporary vellum. N.pl., n.d. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Commedia in Prosa. The play is written in prose. The author could not be identified.
- LITERARY MISCELLANY
  - Parts of Boccaccio's Decamerone and other samples of literary style and rhetoricas phrases. Ms. on paper. 107 ff., including 4 blank leaves. Small 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. N. pl., n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - This volume contains a series of passages chosen for their stylistic elegance from Boccaccio's Decamerone, ff. 1-94. Various sonnets and canzonets in Italian, ff. 95-100. Elegant rhetorical phrases and a fragment of a poem in Italian tercets, ff. 106-107.
- GILIO DA FABRIANIO. SERMO...
  - Gilio de Fabriano. Sermo, de sancto Jubilei anno. Ms. on paper. 3 leaves, 35 numbered pages. Small 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. N. pl., Sept. 24, 1599. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Sermon in Latin on the Holy Jubilee of 1599 by Onofrio Gilio da Fabriano.
- COMEDIES IN PROSE, 4 volumes. Ms. on paper. Together 259 ff. Small
  4to. Contemporary limp vellum.
  - Spina, Ascanio. L'Inconstante. Ms. on paper. 73 ff. The binding is a parchment document in Latin of the 16th or 17th century. N.pl., n.d. (Box 20.1)
  - A comedy play in 5 acts which was acted once in Naples. Presumably this play was not printed.
  - Comedy in Prose. Comedy in prose. No title. Ms. on paper. 64 ff. N.pl., n.d. (Box 20.2)
  - On the first leaf is the following notation in pencil: "Gio. Btta Regni (Begni?) carcerato settimane in secreta il Lottis Balagi," indicating that Regni was either the author or the copyist.
  - Comedy in Prose. Comedy in prose in three acts. Ms. on paper. 64 leaves. N.pl., n.d. (Box 20.3)
  - An untitled play of the heroic-comic genre, with historical personages and stock characters from the commedia dell'arte. One of the central personages seems to be Julian the Apostate. Perhaps this play was named after him? Much pageantry, stage directions call for incidental music.
  - Comedy in Prose. Prose comedy in three acts. Ms. on paper. 133 pp. N.pl., n.d. (Box 20.4)
  - A comedy play, untitled (perhaps by Giovanni Girolamo Benetti, a Roman, whose name appears on verso of the last blank leaf). The genre of this play is a combination of the mythological with the commedia dell'arte world. Typical in this respect is the scene between Pantalone (stock character of the Commedia dell'arte) and Venus (pp. 78-79). Pantalone speaks in the Venetian dialect, Venus in correct standard Italian.
- PARETUS AND RELATED AUTHORS
  Consisting of 8 volumes. 6 or more by Paretus on Philosophy and Sciences, the later ones possibly by other, anonymous authors. Ms. in Latin, on paper. 2758 pages, 18 leaves, 1 drawing of the human brain (vol. 2), and 9 folding diagrams. Small 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. Each volume has an index at the end. N.pl., n.d.
  - Paretus. Institutionem Logicarum. Treatise on the principles of Logic. 203 pages. (Box 21.1)
  - Paretus. Sequel to the proceding. On the sensory faculties, operation of the mind, judgement. pp. 204-654 and index. Drawing of the human brain at beginning. (Box 21.2)
  - Paretus. Continuation. On fantasy, imagination; waking and sleeping state; union of soul and body; refutation of the views of Descartes and Malebranche on this topic; memory, reminiscence. pp. 655-813. (Box 21.3)
  - Paretus. On metaphysics, the existence of God; attributes of god; operations of God; predetermination; man's soul; immortality of the soul; main point of the Aristotelian system; de accidentibus; formae substantiales; the soul of animals; the mechanical explanation of the anima brutorum. 400 pages and 5 leaves. (Box 21.4)
  - Paretus. General introduction to physics: on the essence of the body; divisibility of bodies; elements of chemistry; infinite divisibility of the infinitesimals according to Newton and Leibniz; space; time; the infinite. 362 pages, 2 folding diagrams, 4 leaves index. (Box 21.5)
  - Paretus. On the genesis and nature of sound; on the organ of hearing; the object and sense of smell and touch; on the problem of Gravity: is it possible to construct a ship for navigation in the air? The answer is in the affirmative. Appendix I: longitude and latitude of the earth's regions; size of the earth. Appendix II: on the efficient cause of gravity; geometrical measurements. 377 pages, 9 leaves index, 2 folding diagrams, including a cross section of the human ear and a design for a flying ship. (Box 21.6)
  - Dissertatio de lumine, and other treatises. On Newton's theory of colors; the mechanism of vision; catoptrics; the telescope; electricity. 456 pages, 3 folding diagrams. (Box 21.7)
  - Dissertatio II. De impenetrabilitate. On impenetrability; inertia; second and third Newtonian law; central forces; cause of speed; universal gravity of bodies; laws of gravity; for a better understanding of Newtonian theory; phenomena of tides; Galileo's opinion refuted; Descarte's opinion refuted; Kepler's view refuted; Newton's theory approved; nature of comets. 350 pages, 8 folding diagrams. (Box 21.8)
- BARONIO, CESARE. ANNALES ECCLESIASTICI
  Vol. III, IV. 2 vols. Ms. in Latin. 1170 pages, 13 unnumbered pages. Small 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. N.pl., June 1, 1629-Jan. 30, 1633.
  - Baronio, Ceare. Annales Ecclesiastici. Vol. III. 597 pages and 4 unnumbered pages as index. N.pl., June 1, 1629-July 21, 1630. (Box 22.1)
  - An abridgment of the third tome of the Annales Ecclesiastici by Cardinal Cesare Baronio (1538- 1607).
  - Baronio, Cesare. Annales Ecclesiastici. Vol. IV. 5 unnumbered, 373, 4 unnumbered pages. N.pl., July 22, 1630-January 30, 1633. (Box 22.2)
  - Continuation of the preceding volume. Cardinal Baronio was confessor of Clement VIII, and later chief librarian of the Vatican Library. The Annales Ecclesiastici were published in 12 volumes in Rome, from 1598 to 1607. The present abridgment was compiled between the dates that are indicated at the beginning and at the end of this ms., between 1629 and 1633.
- PRINTED DOCUMENTS.
  - 95 printed broadsides and scrutiny lists with manuscript notes. Folio. Folded and double pages. Original limp vellum. Rome, 1579-1766. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - This volume contains 90 broadsides of appointments of Cardinals by different Popes. With name, woodcut arms, and portraits, mostly printed in red and black, 1624-1766; also 5 printed scrutiny lists with notes by hand, 1597-1671.
- FORTIGUERRI, NICCOLO. IL RICCIARDETTO
  - A poem in octaves, in 30 cantos. Ms. on paper. 197 ff. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. N.pl., n.d. (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Fortiguerri, Niccolo, Il Ricciardetto. A jocular poem: poema eroicomico in calligraphic writing with floral and ornamental title and head pieces at the beginning of each canto. Apparently, Forteguerri, as a result of a bet with friends, composed one canto a day. In each canto he made an effort to fuse the styles and modes of narration of the three major chivalric poems--Pulci's Morgante, Bojardo's Orlando Inamorato, and Ariost's Furioso.
- PROSE COMEDIES
  This volume contains 2 plays and a scenario for a commedia dell'arte. 96 numbered leaves, including 17 blanks. Ms. on paper. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. N.pl., n.d.
  - Il Rodrigo, ovvero la Costanza in Amore. Play. Name of author not given. 38 leaves, numbered 1-38. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - La Pellegrina. Play. No author's name. 36 leaves, numbered ff. 39-73. (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - A scenario for a commedia dell'arte. No author or title given. 6 leaves, numbered ff. 91-96. (Box 26, Folder 3)
- LEGAL DICTIONARY
  - This volume contains a dictionary of Latin legal terms. Ms. on paper. 299 leaves. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. N.pl., n.d. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - At the end, long lists of names, ranged according to dates. The dictionary is partly thumb-indexed.
- PTOLEMAEUS, CLAUDIUS. GEOGRAPHIA.
  - Edited by Giuseppe Moleto. 4 leaves, 112, 186 pages, blank leaves, 32 leaves (some light damp marks). With 63 (of 64) engraved double page maps, text on the versos. 4to. Contemporary vellum. Venice, Vincentio Valgrisi, 1562. (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Ptolemaeus, Claudius, Geographia. An important Ptolemy edition. Giuseppe Moleto from Messina (1531-1588), professor of mathematics in Padua, revised the Latin translation by Willibald Pirckheimer and supplied an extensive commentary to books 1 and 7. The very fine engraved maps had first appeared in Ruscelli's Italian Ptolemy edition. All except four are based upon Gastaldi's maps to the pocket edition of 1548. Ruscelli's maps are extremely well designed and became very influential in the development of cartography. His world map (no. 2) is the first engraved representation of the world divided into two spheres, the right half showing the old and the left half showing the new world. The following nine maps refer to America: Orbis descriptio; Tierra Nova; Brasil Nuova Tavola; Nueva Hispania; Tierra Nueva; Isola Spagnola Nova; Septentrionalium Partium Nova Tabula; Isola Cuva Nova; Schonlandia Nova. The second world map, "Carta Marina," (No. 3) is lacking in this copy.
  - Sabin 66489; Harrisse 239 (incomplete); J.C. Brown I (1), p. 217; Ricciardi II, 163 ("Bella e rara ediz."); Nordenskioeld, Faksimile-Atlas, p. 29.
- MISCELLANY, 60 documents (irregularly numbered 1-49), 42 of them
  in manuscript, 18 in print. 860 pages and 4 pages index. In Italian and Latin. Folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, c. 1640-1736.
  - Spolverino, Ottavanio. Disfeda alli Signori Giovanni Francesco Bevilaqua e Marchese Horazio Canossa. 44 printed folio pages, folded, numbered ff. 3-24. Printed documents in the legal suit of Spolverino against Bevilaqua and Canossa, dated from 1648 to 1657. The last 2 leaves slightly defective. N.p., n.d. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Fattione seguita in Roma fra il Marchese de Los Veles Amb. di Spagna et il Vescovo di Lamego, Amb. di Portogallo fatto li 20 Agosto 1640. Ms. document. 6 pages, numbered ff. 25-28. Small 4to. Ms. report on the controversy between the Spanish and Portuguese ambassadors in Rome, on Aug. 20, 1640. At the end, an epigram in Latin on the affair. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Ristretto del Processo e della Sentenza contra Michele Molinos...Ms. in Italian. 7 pages, numbered ff. 29-32. Concerning the process by the Jesuits and the Inquisition against Michele Molinos, Spanish Quietist in Rome. He was arrested in Rome in 1685. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Errori principali intorno la nuova contemplatione overo Oratione di quieti. 1685. Ms. in Italian. 5 pages, numbered ff. 33-35. Contains 19 points concerning the dogma of Quietism. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Copia di fatto scritto ad un Cavaliere. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages, numbered 36-39. Concerns a controversy between a Marchese Fontana and a Count Aldrovani which occured on Feb. 26, 1686 on account of a horse. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Contrasto Curioso tra il Governatore d'una Citta ed il vescovo... Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 40-41. Concerns a controversy between the governor of a city and a bishop. Undated. (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - A Cavalieri. Printed letter, dated June 14, 1689, signed by Francesco Maria Vaini and Alesandro Mignanelli. 3 4to pages, with an insert of a 3 page printed letter in 8vo, signed by hand by Ottavio del Bufalo, dated May 6, 1689. Concerning a controversy between three gentlemen. Numbered ff. 42-45. (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Acciaioli, Ruberto. Relazione del successo e delli Accidenti del Matrimonio del Cavaliere Ruberto Acciaioli con la Signora Lisabetta Mormorai... Printed document, 10 pages, numbered ff. 46-52. Various documents 1690-1691 concerning the marriage between R. Acciaioli and Lisabetta Mormorai. (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Galanterie di due Fr. Minori non-Osservanti de S. Francisco. Ms. in Italian. 61 pages, numbered ff. 54-85. Concerning a French and an Italian member of the Order of the Minorites. Dates mentioned are August to October 1697. (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Ristretto del processo e sentenza contra Simone Leoni...della Diocesi di Como. Ms. in Italian, 3 pages, numbered ff. 86-87. Undated. (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Ristretto della Sentenza contro Antonio Maria Leoni da Scabiegla...della Diocese di Como. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 88-89. Legal sentences against Antonio Maria Leoni. Undated. (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Baldeschi-Colonna, Cardinal Frederigo. Difesa. Ms. in Italian. 20 pages, numbered ff. 90-99. Defense of Cardinal Baldeschi, who was nuncio in Switzerland. No date (after 1657). (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Crescenzi, Serlupi. Lettera scritta al Alessandro Capizucchi. Ms. in Italian. 1 page (f. 100). Dated 25 Jan., 1598. A letter of resentment and reproaches. (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Ristretto della sentenza di Fra Pietro Paolo di San Giovanni Evangelista Agostiniana Scalzo, abjurato di 26.novembre 1698. Ms. in Italian. 7 pages, numbered ff. 101-104. Small 4to. Judgement against an Augustinian painter. (Box 29, Folder 13a)